<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">
   <para>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="embedded:graphics1" width="1.5929inch" depth="0.5102inch"/>
   </para>
   <para>Project 2nd Reporting Period Review Meeting</para>
   <para>Date: 23/04/2011 - 24/04/2011</para><sect1><title>Logistics</title>
   <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row>
            <entry>
               <para>Organizing partner</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
               <para>FFZG, Tilde</para>
               <para/>
            </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
            <entry>
               <para>Contact information</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
               <para>Marko Tadić</para>
               <para>GSM +385 99 2537 194</para>
               <para>marko.tadic@ffzg.hr</para>
            </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
            <entry>
               <para>Venue</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
               <para>Centre for Advanced Academic Studies (CAAS) of the Universtiy of Zagreb</para>
               <para>Frana Bulića 4</para>
               <para>20000 Dubrovnik</para>
            </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
            <entry>
               <para>Getting to the venue</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
               <para>Arrival in Dubrovnik: When arriving to Dubrovnik Airport you can take a taxi to your respective accommodation (the price is around 200 HRK, approx. 30 EUR). The journey takes about 25 minutes. You can also take a bus that leaves the airport after every landing of regular flights and takes you to the City. These buses will be marked on the window shield with the sign Airport – Dubrovnik and the bus fare is 35 HRK (approx. 5 EUR). You can take the bus from the airport to the Pile stop or Central Bus </para>
               <para/>
               <para>Terminal. Both are equally distant from the Hotel Lero and on both locations there is a local bus and taxi stand. The bus ticket can be purchased at any newsstand. Taxi can also be reached at any place and any time by calling Radio taxi service (020) 970. </para>
               <para>You can get more details at web page <ulink url="http://hnk.ffzg.hr/fassbl2010/venue.html">http://hnk.ffzg.hr/fassbl2010/venue.html</ulink> which was prepared for a conference back in 2010.</para>
            </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
            <entry>
               <para>Hotel</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
               <para>Hotel Lero</para>
               <para>Iva Vojnovića 14</para>
               <para>20000 Dubrovnik</para>
               <para>All relevant hotel details are available at <ulink url="http://www.hotel-lero.hr/">http://www.hotel-lero.hr/</ulink>
               </para>
               <para>From hotel to CASS there is 10-12 min walk</para>
            </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
            <entry>
               <para>Catering</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
               <para>Lunch on Monday and Tuesday will be covered by FFZG while dinner will be on our own.</para>
               <para>Suggestion is that all that have already arrived meet  on Sunday at 20:00 in front of the western gate to the old town (Pile Gate) and from there we can walk and find a suitable restaurant. </para>
               <para>The same we can repeat Monday evening.</para>
            </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
            <entry>
               <para>Additional value</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
               <para>If there will be interest, we can organise a guided city tour in English on Monday afternoon. Please, notify Andris about your interest.</para>
            </entry>
         </row></tbody></tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
      <para/>
      <para/>
      <para/>
   </para></sect1><para>2</para>
   <para/>
</article>